Wilmer Waldo Papers 1969-039
University of Houston Libraries Special Collections
Wilmer Waldo Papers
1894-1957
1894-1920
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Waldo, Wilmer
1969-039
35 Linear Feet
Comprised of a Project File and a Subject File, materials in the collection date from 1894-1957 and include project blueprints, correspondence, financials, reports, maps, and field notes. Project File materials document Waldo's professional activities, ranging from construction and site planning to worksite and employee management. These materials document major projects, such as the Beaumont, Sour Lake, and Western Railway and the layout of Rice University, and smaller projects, such as the movement and reconstruction of the Waldo Mansion to its present Westmoreland location. Collection materials also include personal correspondence, financials, maps, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, and a small amount of material related to the teaching career of Gentry Waldo, Wilmer Waldo's brother.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Wilmer Waldo was born in Houston in 1876 to J.P. and Mary Virginia Gentry Waldo. Educated in Civil Engineering at Princeton University, Waldo was instrumental in the planning and execution of myriad public and private infrastructure projects in the city of Houston and beyond. While perhaps most known for his role in planning the layout of the campus of Rice University, Waldo also contributed to railway construction projects in service of the Suderman-Dolson and Fred A. Jones Companies and completed numerous projects in the Houston community and across Southeast Texas as an individual contractor. In 1902, Waldo led the effort to move the now-famous Waldo Mansion from the original location at the corner of Rusk and Caroline to its present location on Westmoreland Avenue. Waldo resided in the mansion with his siblings until his death in 1962.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
Comprised of a Project File and a Subject File, materials in the collection date from 1894-1957 and include project blueprints, correspondence, financials, reports, maps, and field notes. Project File materials document Waldo's professional activities, ranging from construction and site planning to worksite and employee management. These materials document major projects, such as the Beaumont, Sour Lake, and Western Railway and the layout of Rice University, and smaller projects, such as the movement and reconstruction of the Waldo Mansion to its present Westmoreland location. Collection materials also include personal correspondence, financials, maps, scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, and a small amount of material related to the teaching career of Gentry Waldo, Wilmer Waldo's brother.
Architectural drawings (visual works); Correspondence; Architecture; Rice University; City Planning; Houston (Tex.); Waldo, Wilmer
- Project File, 1894-1939; 24 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  The Project File series is comprised of 24 boxes of material. Materials are arranged chronologically by project and include project blueprints, correspondence, financials, reports, maps, and field notes.
  - Texas and Orleans Railway Company, 1894-1896; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mound Oil Company, 1894; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Buffalo Bayou Survey, 1897; 1 folders (Drawer S.15)
  - Denison-Sherman Interurban Railway, 1901; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Waldo Mansion Move, Westmoreland, 1902; 5 folders (Box 1, Folder 5-8, Drawer S.15)
  - Marmion, Angleton Property, 1902; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - H.F. McGregor, 1902; 3 folders (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - W.W. Haskins Pasture, 1902; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Waters Pierce Oil Company, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - James Merry, League City, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sterling Meyer Fairgrounds Land and Investment Company, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James Lawlor, 1903; 2 folders (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - J.N. Hall, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lovejoy and Malevinsky, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Turley v. Texas and New Orleans Railroad Company Consultation, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - F.J. DeMerritt, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lily C. DeWalt, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hill Brown Rice Land and Irrigation Company, 1903; 1 folders (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Atlanta Georgia and Shelbyville Illinois, 1938-1942; Undated; 1 folders (Box 33, Folder 6, Box 34, Folder 1-5)